Belachew Haile-Mariam



belachewhm.github.io belachewhm@gmail.com

Full-Stack Software Engineer with experience in Java, Web Development, DevOps, and Automation. I excel in fast-paced environments, and always place myself in team leadership roles. My technical background is very versatile, and I enjoy learning new things on the spot. It keeps life interesting!

Employment History

Capital One

Software Engineer, Plano, TX April 2017 – Present

Software Engineering

- Designed and implemented a testing solution that involved wrapping a Spring Boot application around existing Selenium/Cucumber test automation, and exposing it as a set of RESTful web services and a custom SwaggerUI interface. The application was then Dockerized, and deployed to AWS for start of day production validations, infrastructure rehydrations, and L3 production support application monitoring
- Refactored and added new features to an internal application that tracks the progress of home loans as they move from the originations to servicing department
- Automated a manual audit by using Java to cross reference Splunk logs with loan processing data to validate that our department was following proper regulations

Production Support

- Supporting production deployments
- Testing/Validating infrastructure rehydrations
- Solved over 100 customer digital escalations

DevOps

- Migrated Jenkins build jobs from an on-prem Jenkins 1.x instance to a Jenkins 2.x instance running on AWS
- Utilized GitHub, Jenkins, and cURL to automate part of our QA and Production deployments to AWS

Fidelity Investments

Software Engineer, Westlake, TX Jan 2017 – Mar 2017

DevOps

- Reverse engineered a java web application from a WAR file (created through an Ant build) into a mult-module Maven project, while simultaneously migrating the application from Subversion to Git. This shrunk the size of the code base down from over 4 GB to approximately 45 MB, and greatly improved the consistency and build time of each CI/CD build
- Created Batch scripts that utilize Chocolatey (https://chocolatey.org/) to automatically download, install, and configure software on Windows machines
- Installed Jenkins slave agents to run on virtual Windows machines, and configured them to be resilient and stay online as much as possible

Test Automation

- Migrated over 50 test automation source code repositories from SVN to Git, and renamed each project to follow a consistent naming convention to make them more easily identifiable
- Introduced the Allure Reporting Framework (https://github.com/allure-framework/) to my team, which provided a consistent way to showcase test results and test metrics
- Created a Maven project that defined clear and specific build goals for compilation, testing, packaging, installation, deployment, and reporting. This was then used as a parent project to all our other maven test automation projects, which provided my team with clean and consistent automated tests and reporting

Associate Software Engineer, Westlake, TX January 2016 – January 2017

DevOps

- Developed a migration strategy to move development teams and their code repositories from Subversion to Git
- Facilitated training sessions to teach basic source control concepts using Git, Stash, SourceTree, and different development workflows (Central Repository, Feature Branches, Gitflow)
- Onboarded new applications to a Continuous Integration/Continuous Deployment pipeline, and modified existing CI/CD pipelines as needed
- Made improvements to an existing DevOps dashboard to showcase metrics such as code coverage, deployment metrics, application compliance, etc.

Test Automation

- Worked in a development team to create and maintain a library of common test automation functions in Java
- Migrated Java applications from Ant to Maven, and moved artifacts out of source control repositories into artifact repositories (Nexus, Artifactory)
- Upgraded and configured Java/Spring projects as needed
- Converted manual test cases into automated tests, and incorporated them into existing CI/CD pipelines

Associate Software Engineer, Cary, NC August 2015 – December 2015

Leap Program

- Completed Software Engineering training modules on Object-Oriented Analysis & Design, UNIX Essentials,
 Oracle 11g & Data Modeling, Big Data, Java/XML, The Spring Framework, Service Oriented Architecture,
 Developing Dynamic Web Applications, and C# Programming
- Developed an automated system for Fidelity's Asset Management division to import, normalize, and store big
 data from credit rating agencies into a Hadoop environment. This allowed the firm to find credit rating
 mismatches between those original ratings and data imported from credit rating aggregation services, potentially
 saving the company millions of dollars in future liabilities

Technical Intern, Westlake, TX

June 2014 – August 2014

- Constructed a single page web application to showcase project overviews and associated metrics
- Tested RESTful web services for security vulnerabilities, proper inputs/outputs, and overall responsiveness

❖ Ayoka Systems

Web Application Developer Intern, Arlington, TX June 2013 – May 2014 (1 Year)

- Designed, built, and modified web applications using the Grails framework and MVC architecture
- Tested applications to verify that product specifications have been properly met

Education

University of Texas at Arlington – Bachelor of Science in Computer Engineering, Arlington, TX

Bachelor of Science in Computer Engineering, May 2015

- Senior Design Project Leader, Team SmartGrass (September 2014 May 2015)
- College of Engineering Student Ambassador (January 2015 May 2015)
- Founding Father of the Theta-Omega Chapter of the Kappa Sigma Fraternity (November 2013 May 2015)